<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-01-17T21:41:24+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">moutreach</title><subtitle>popular style research environment
</subtitle><author><name>Massimo Pizzol</name></author><entry><title type="html">Surviving co-authorship</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/01/17/good-authorship-practices.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Surviving co-authorship" /><published>2017-01-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-01-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/01/17/good%20authorship%20practices</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/01/17/good-authorship-practices.html">&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/el_gir_bw.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Elephant_Giraffe&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt; Ganesha to giraffe: &quot;With my four hands I shall be both first and second author&quot;. (Photo: Massimo Pizzol)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing scientific papers is hard. Dealing with co-authorship issues is harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here below I wrote a bullet-point list of what I believe are good co-authorship practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;These are lessons learnt from problems I run into or mistakes I did.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote them here as a reminder to myself. If they are useful for you too, well…good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Always remember that…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) &lt;strong&gt;Nobody&lt;/strong&gt;, no matter his/her position, is entitled to be co-author by default&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) &lt;strong&gt;Only&lt;/strong&gt; substantial contributions lead to co-authorship&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) &lt;strong&gt;The first author&lt;/strong&gt; is in the best position to evaluate which contributions were substantial&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A paper is a project and thus requires project management…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Deal with authorship issues &lt;strong&gt;openly and transparently&lt;/strong&gt;. Bring them up for discussion instead of avoiding them. They will pop out anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) Discuss authorship before doing the research/experiments, and &lt;strong&gt;always before you start writing&lt;/strong&gt; the paper. This means also clarifying with potential co-authors mutual expectations from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6) Make a research plan and a &lt;strong&gt;writing plan&lt;/strong&gt; with realistic milestones and concrete tasks. It allows keeping track of contributions. It is then easy to look back and check who did/delivered what and when in case of controversies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7) Use the &lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/strong&gt; section. Those who helped by reading a draft and giving comments, advices, and opinions are not co-authors, but deserve a formal “thank you” in the Acknowledgements (note: always ask the person before doing it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bonus, number eight…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8) In an &lt;em&gt;ideal&lt;/em&gt; world, the previous points would be enough. Yet co-authorship is a &lt;strong&gt;sensible topic&lt;/strong&gt;. Sometimes troubles are inevitable and somebody gets pissed off. Seek the advice of a senior colleague or peer in case of serious problems. Reading the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.icmje.org/icmje-recommendations.pdf&quot;&gt;Vancouver reccomendations&lt;/a&gt; can be of concrete help too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Massimo Pizzol</name></author><category term="authorship" /><category term="scientific writing" /><summary type="html">Seven good practices for co-authoring scientific papers</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sustainable Himalayan buildings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/01/03/Himalayan-buildings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sustainable Himalayan buildings" /><published>2017-01-03T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-01-03T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/01/03/Himalayan-buildings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/01/03/Himalayan-buildings.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This guest post narrated in first person by Silu Bhochhibhoya&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; describes her amazing work&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; on sustainable buildings in the Himalaya to which I contributed for the modelling part.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Hpeak.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Himalayan-peak-pic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;View from Khumjung village (Photo: Silu Bhochhibhoya)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-himalaya&quot;&gt;Why Himalaya&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been interested in trekking since my childhood when my father used to take us for hiking nearby our town in Nepal. I am fascinated by the mountains, their people, their lifestyle, food, and culture. I brought this passion into my universities studies and later on into my research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing temperature in the Himalayas is creating serious impacts on this unique mountain environment. &lt;em&gt;And so does the human presence.&lt;/em&gt; In the Himalayan region the &lt;a href=&quot;http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/120&quot;&gt;Sagarmatha National Park&lt;/a&gt; is a key touristic destination due to its natural beauty. That’s also where the highest peak in the world lies: &lt;strong&gt;Mount Everest&lt;/strong&gt;. In 2014 the Park received almost &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nepalmountainnews.com/cms/archives/79654&quot;&gt;37000 tourist visits&lt;/a&gt; and these are increasing by 3% every year. With the growing number of tourist visiting the area new buildings are being constructed to satisfy the &lt;strong&gt;demand for lodging&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buildings in the park have historically been built with an &lt;a href=&quot;http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0002/000299/029926eo.pdf&quot;&gt;ancestral Sherpa house design&lt;/a&gt; using locally available materials. Yet the new buildings have a modern design and use imported construction materials that allow for better insulation but have to be &lt;strong&gt;transported via helicopter&lt;/strong&gt; from the capital city Kathmandu. The terrain is too difficult for road transport. It is thus unclear &lt;em&gt;which of the two building types is the best one, environmentally speaking&lt;/em&gt;, and I wanted to find it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More specifically, I was interested in investigating what are the environmental and economic implications of &lt;em&gt;modern versus traditional&lt;/em&gt; ways of building lodgings in the area. This comparison should be done considering the entire &lt;em&gt;life cycle&lt;/em&gt; of the buildings. How are the raw materials extracted and manufactured? How is the building constructed? What about the energy use during daily activities? And the building maintenance and replacement of materials? I chose to compare three different commercial building types which are common lodging options in the Park: modern, semi-modern, and traditional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;getting-the-data-at-high-altitude&quot;&gt;Getting the data at high altitude&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have collected most of the data in the field during March and April 2014, via questionnaires and measurements. What I did is about &lt;strong&gt;50 structured interviews&lt;/strong&gt; with hotel owners, who were very co-operative and kind. What I asked them is the &lt;em&gt;type of materials&lt;/em&gt; each building was made of, and whether these materials had been fetched &lt;em&gt;locally&lt;/em&gt;, plus how much &lt;em&gt;fuels and energy&lt;/em&gt; were used in different activities like cooking and heating. I also asked for or retrieved the &lt;em&gt;price&lt;/em&gt; of each material and fuel used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Hinterviews.png&quot; alt=&quot;Himalayan-Interview-pic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Questionnaire survey in the Park (Photo: Silu Bhochhibhoya)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then &lt;strong&gt;I measured each building&lt;/strong&gt;: length, breadth, and height of doors, windows, walls, floors. This was a necessary step to &lt;em&gt;quantify the amount of the materials used&lt;/em&gt; for the construction of each building.  When I returned back to my office I made a model for each building, using a specific software and database that contain information on the environmental impact of each material. With the model I could calculate the environmental and economic impacts of lodging in three existing buildings in the Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;which-is-the-best-building&quot;&gt;Which is the best building?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the three chosen, &lt;strong&gt;the modern building showed the highest environmental impact&lt;/strong&gt; (in terms of carbon footprint) and cost over the lifetime of 50 years. The transportation and manufacturing-related impacts overcome the benefits of better insulation performance of commercial materials. The use stage was responsible for the largest share of the impacts over the building lifetime, this showing how impacting is the energy use for different household activities such as cooking, space heating, lighting, heating water etc. These are the activities where the main improvement opportunities lie. The way forward for new construction projects in the Himalayan region is the &lt;strong&gt;balance&lt;/strong&gt; between using locally available materials in the building construction while ensuring insulation and the use of renewable energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;more-data-and-more-culture&quot;&gt;More data and more culture&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have collected data for 50 buildings, but only three of them were analyzed in detail due to time and resources constraints, and to keep model complexity manageable. However, the next step is comparing between more buildings and checking if the results obtained so far have a more &lt;strong&gt;general validity&lt;/strong&gt;. Moreover, in my study I didn’t take into account important &lt;em&gt;cultural factors&lt;/em&gt; that are associated with the traditional buildings. The traditional buildings &lt;strong&gt;embody the Parks’ cultural heritage&lt;/strong&gt; and are a characteristic feature in the Park. Including this aspect in the analysis is an essential step towards the sustainability assessments of buildings in the Park, side by side with the environmental and economic aspects I already focused on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Silu is a Nepalese researcher who just completed her PhD studies at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unipd.it/international-highlights/node/82&quot;&gt;Department of Land, Environment, Agriculture and Forestry&lt;/a&gt; of the University of Padua, Italy.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhochhibhoya S, Pizzol M, Achten WMJ, Maskey RK, Zanetti M, Cavalli R. Comparative life cycle assessment and life cycle costing of lodging in the Himalaya. The International Journal of Life Cycle Assessment (2016). &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11367-016-1212-8&quot;&gt;doi:10.1007/s11367-016-1212-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Massimo Pizzol</name></author><category term="articles" /><category term="life cycle assessment" /><summary type="html">A study on the environmental impact of modern versus traditional construction methods</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections on the yearly research group seminar</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/19/Reflections-on-research-group-seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections on the yearly research group seminar" /><published>2016-12-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-12-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2016/12/19/Reflections-on-research-group-seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/19/Reflections-on-research-group-seminar.html">&lt;p&gt;I have just attended our yearly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.en.dcea.dk/&quot;&gt;DCEA&lt;/a&gt; research group seminar. But what is it really about, why are we doing it, and what makes it a great experience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/vessel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fishing-vessels-pic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Stranded boats nearby the seminar venue in Northern Jutland, Denmark (Photo: Massimo Pizzol)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-setting&quot;&gt;The setting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We meet once a year for two consecutive days. Usually the venue is chosen &lt;strong&gt;close to nature and far from the offices&lt;/strong&gt;, so that we can take walks and fresh air. The place should be able to host the entire group (approx. 10 people this time) for the night and have a seminar room. It can be more or less low-cost depending on the budget available. For instance, last year we rented a scout-hut and prepared food ourselves (amazing slow-cooked roast by Ole and Anne), this time we stayed at a hotel with service. The program is organized in blocks of two hours and is rather flexible, the block activities are co-organized by the participants around one or two main themes, and include open air activities too. Then there is a social program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-content&quot;&gt;The content&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the topics of this year were particularly interesting and relevant and that is what made the meeting very successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first issue we addressed is &lt;strong&gt;funding&lt;/strong&gt;. And we really approached it comprehensively. This went from a general-level discussion (powered by an internal expert) about how to improve the applications process as a group to increase success rate, to discussing concrete oncoming applications, to the very practical exercise of reading and commenting each other’s past applications and new ideas. This was also a chance to hear success stories and failure stories. These activities inevitably lead to a discussion of our research strategy, its critical revision, and a brainstorm of what is our research vision as individual scientists and as a group. The outcome was somehow not conclusive but I think &lt;strong&gt;the process was far more important than the outcome&lt;/strong&gt; in this case, as we had a necessary reflection on who we ultimately are as a group. For example, we observed how many similarities there are in the past and oncoming research in life cycle assessment and environmental impact assessment, despite the evident differences between the two tools and type of approaches and methods used in the respective scientific communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second issue we addressed is &lt;strong&gt;work ethics&lt;/strong&gt;. In particular we discussed and compared practices regarding authorship of scientific articles: when is somebody a co-author, what is a substantial contribution? What are the problems we encountered and how we solved them? We also touched on data sharing: when and how is appropriate to share data, to what extent should be done to achieve a good balance between being open to the research community but also protect our own work? What if others use our research material and data for writing publications? &lt;strong&gt;Who owns the data&lt;/strong&gt; in a group context, and in a collaborative project context? What are advantages and limitations of working open source for us? And again we exchanged experiences in data protection and sharing, good practices, success and failure stories. For example I learnt a lot about the issues in storing and sharing interview data and in general on data sharing in social sciences, that was quite enlightening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/walk.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Walk-on-the-beach-pic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Walking and discussing (Photo: Massimo Pizzol)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-reflection&quot;&gt;The reflection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two key points that I particularly appreciate about the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The seminar is about sharing.&lt;/strong&gt; It’s amazing how easily you can lose track of others’ work progress even if they sit in an office two meters from yours. So it is the moment to make a status and share our current and recent activities and achievements and get updated. Then there is the sharing of ideas and future plans, which is made possible by the open environment, where one can feel comfortable telling about personal research plans, get feedback, and ask questions to others. And last but not least there is the sharing of experiences in a learning perspective. &lt;strong&gt;For me it is really instructive to hear what other colleagues went through&lt;/strong&gt; regarding e.g. applications, papers, projects, etc. This is useful to anticipate future problems and plan ahead, and to see what are different approaches or problems in a dynamically changing academic world.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a typical Danish style &lt;strong&gt;there is a flat hierarchy at the seminar.&lt;/strong&gt; PhD students and professors sit at the same table and discuss the same issues. This is a tremendous learning opportunity for the junior staff. &lt;em&gt;I had no idea of what an application looked like before reading some here at the seminar!&lt;/em&gt; said one of our PhD colleagues, just to make a simple example. We grow better researchers this way.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-social&quot;&gt;The social&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like it or not, we are people before being researchers. And people like beautiful things! Beautiful nature like frozen sand dunes, a giant moon, and a pastel colored sky are breathtaking. Food and drinks quality definitely lived up to the standards of a very picky Italian. And good talks where I realized I don’t have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Totem&quot;&gt;totem&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_animal&quot;&gt;spirit animal&lt;/a&gt; (where can you find a shaman on google and order one?) are an essential success factor for the event. Next time we plan a &lt;em&gt;pony-ride&lt;/em&gt; though so maybe we have something to work on…! Closing on DCEA’s 2016 seminar and looking forward to next year’s one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Massimo Pizzol</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="social" /><summary type="html">What is it about and why I think it was great</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wood networks are nice</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/07/Marginal-suppliers-NA-wood.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wood networks are nice" /><published>2016-12-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-12-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2016/12/07/Marginal-suppliers-NA-wood</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/07/Marginal-suppliers-NA-wood.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/Network.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Network screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written this article&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; together with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.geomar.de/en/mitarbeiter/fb3/eoe/eoe-n/mscotti/&quot;&gt;Marco&lt;/a&gt; and I am really proud of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-we-did-it&quot;&gt;Why we did it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wanted to answer a simple question: &lt;strong&gt;where does the wood of tomorrow come from?&lt;/strong&gt; This is an important question because many are looking at wood as future energy source or construction material. Energy from waste wood residues may contribute to reducing our dependency from fossil fuels, as woody feedstock can be used for heating and for producing liquid fuels too. In fact, this study was part of the larger &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.et.aau.dk/research-programmes/biomass/activities/c3bo/&quot;&gt;C3BO project&lt;/a&gt; on producing fuel from wood residues. Wood is also praised as a sustainable construction material and future substitute of cement. &lt;em&gt;So who is going to produce all this wood and where?&lt;/em&gt; Once we figure this out, we can investigate in detail what impact wood production will have on the environment in terms of land occupation and emissions. This will allow making better informed decisions and evaluate which energy source and construction material is more &lt;strong&gt;eco-efficient&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-we-did-it&quot;&gt;How we did it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To answer this question we had to study the market of wood products. We live in the times of globalization, so products are traded globally. However, to what extent is this the case for wood products? Chips and particles are light and cheap, but sawn wood is heavy and costly. So there must be differences in the way they are traded. The market may be &lt;strong&gt;not that global&lt;/strong&gt; after all. There may be many local markets instead. We looked at trade data from &lt;a href=&quot;http://faostat.fao.org/&quot;&gt;FAOSTAT&lt;/a&gt;. These show the amount of wood products exchanged by all countries in the world via exports and imports, in the last 15 years. &lt;strong&gt;We realized that this was a &lt;em&gt;network&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;! A trade network to be precise. At that point we knew that we could use some powerful mathematical tools (&lt;em&gt;network analysis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;clustering algorithms&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to crunch the data and see whether the trade network was fragmented into smaller networks, called &lt;em&gt;communities&lt;/em&gt;, and whether these could represent &lt;strong&gt;geographical markets&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-we-found&quot;&gt;What we found&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found that the wood trade network could be actually split into smaller geographical markets, which correspond to our communities. Most interestingly the trade network of each wood product was fragmented in a different way. For some products like wood pulp we could observe a huge, global market, with several countries trading between each other. For some other products like sawn wood we could see many different markets with countries trading with their neighbors only. The nice thing is that in the fragmented networks &lt;strong&gt;the identified communities matched quite well existing geographical areas&lt;/strong&gt;, e.g. Northern Europe and Asia. This confirmed our expectation that the markets relate to geographical proximity, trade areas (e.g. the EU), and the combination of both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What next?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well this was not sufficient to fully answer our initial question. We had to do some other things too, like checking if these geographical markets &lt;strong&gt;changed over time&lt;/strong&gt; (they were pretty stable in the last 15 years), and finding who are the most successful countries to produce wood products in each market. Why this last part? Because we assumed that &lt;strong&gt;today’s most successful producers will be tomorrow’s suppliers of wood&lt;/strong&gt;. We used a simple approach here. We calculated whether the production of wood products in each country had been increasing or decreasing over the last 15  years. Unfortunately, the results were not robust and changed too much depending on the time-span under analysis, indicating that a more advanced model would be needed. &lt;strong&gt;Ouch!&lt;/strong&gt; We’ll take it from here in our next study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pizzol M, Scotti M, Identifying marginal supplying countries of wood products via trade network analysis, The International Journal of Life Cycle Assessment (2016)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11367-016-1222-6&quot;&gt;doi:10.1007/s11367-016-1222-6&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The R code used for doing this analysis is available at my github &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/massimopizzol/Wood_trade_network_analysis&quot;&gt;profile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Massimo Pizzol</name></author><category term="articles" /><category term="network" /><category term="wood" /><summary type="html">I have written this article together with Marco and I am really proud of it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finally online</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/11/23/finally-online.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finally online" /><published>2016-11-23T23:15:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-11-23T23:15:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2016/11/23/finally-online</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2016/11/23/finally-online.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;moutreach-lives&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;moutreach&lt;/strong&gt; lives!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it’s time to gradually upload content…so let’s start breaking the ice. &lt;strong&gt;The first feeling of being online is a mix of excitement and fear&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excitement for having succeeded with the practical implementation. I am so happy to be using Jekyll to put this blog together. I have taken the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/minima&quot;&gt;minima&lt;/a&gt; theme and modified only a bit, can’t do more with my current skills, but honestly I am not interested in graphic layout too much anyway. It has been a steep learning curve since I am not a web programmer at all (didn’t even know what html was before starting…). Almost a DYI project. However, &lt;strong&gt;great satisfaction and feeling of ownership&lt;/strong&gt; now that everything is settled into place!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excitement because this space opens for a lot of &lt;strong&gt;new communication and dissemination possibilities&lt;/strong&gt; compared to my current academic outreach. I felt for a long time the need to bring my work to the attention of a larger public. I don’t think it makes sense to keep it confined to the academic audience. Not because what I do is more important or deserves more attention than what others’ do. It is more like a (&lt;em&gt;moral?&lt;/em&gt;) obligation. Bringing the research results to the public, and making the effort to communicate them in comprehensible ways…I think is part of my job. As simple as that. Also, this is a space to present views I have on general research topics (peer-review, authorships, etc.), and teaching that I can’t publish elsewhere. Hopefully I’ll get feedback to initiate some discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fear because I hope to live up to the blogging task…so far so good though, fingers crossed and looking forward to the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-people-to-thank-already&quot;&gt;Some people to thank already:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emanuele&lt;/strong&gt; for technical support in general and in the domain choice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://meedabyte.com/2012/07/13/simonecicero/&quot;&gt;Simone&lt;/a&gt; for encouraging me to start a blog&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://matthewcashmore.net/&quot;&gt;Matthew&lt;/a&gt; for discussing the potential and feasibility of a research blog&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anita&lt;/strong&gt; for saying the graphic layout was not that terrible after all…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://spector.io/how-to-set-up-github-pages-with-a-custom-domain-on-gandi/&quot;&gt;who wrote this blog post&lt;/a&gt; on domain settings. THANK YOU, I was completely lost with DNS, CNAME etc…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Massimo Pizzol</name></author><summary type="html">moutreach lives!</summary></entry></feed>
